<div1>
<head lang="eng" orth_orig="ACT">act</head>
<sense pos="v" n="v." level="1">
<sense level="2">Do, <foreign lang="la">agere, facere </foreign>(<foreign lang="la">agere</foreign>, like <foreign lang="gr">πράττειν</foreign>, refers more to the simple acting than to the results of it; <foreign lang="la">facere</foreign>, like <foreign lang="gr">ποιεῖν</foreign>, refers to the action qnd its results: to act well or ill, <foreign lang="la">recte</foreign> or <foreign lang="la">male agere</foreign>, and <foreign lang="la">recte</foreign> or <foreign lang="la">male facere</foreign>; but the latter only so far as the effect of the action is, or is not, what it should be).</sense><sense level="2">Behave, <foreign lang="la">se gerere</foreign> (e.g., shamefully). To act like a man, <foreign lang="la">virum se praestare</foreign>.</sense><sense level="2">Exert force, <foreign lang="la">vim habere</foreign> (not <foreign lang="la">vim exserere</foreign>, which is not Latin): <foreign lang="la">efficacem esse</foreign> (to work or be effective). The medicine acts, <foreign lang="la">cincipitur venis medicamentum</foreign>: does not act <foreign lang="la">meicamentum imbecillius est quam morbus</foreign>: the medicine acts so powerfully, <foreign lang="la">tanta vis est medicamenti</foreign>: the medicine acts well, <foreign lang="la">commode facit</foreign> (<author>Celsus</author>). To act upon anything, <foreign lang="la">vim habere</foreign> or <foreign lang="la">exercere in aliquid</foreign>: on anybody, <foreign lang="la">aliquem</foreign> or <foreign lang="la">alicujus animum movere</foreign>, <foreign lang="la">commovere</foreign>. It acts upon me in different ways, <foreign lang="la">vanie afficior aliqua re</foreign>. It acts differently upon me, <foreign lang="la">aliquid aliter fero</foreign>.</sense><sense level="2">To be in effective action; of things, <foreign lang="la">in effectu esse</foreign> (e.g., machines).</sense><sense level="2">Act a part on the stage, or in life, <foreign lang="la">agere aliquem</foreign> or <foreign lang="la">alicujus partes</foreign>; <foreign lang="la">alicujus personam tueri</foreign> (not <foreign lang="la">alicujus personam agere</foreign>): <foreign lang="la">simulare aliquem</foreign>, or with accusative and infinitive (to pretend to be anybody). <foreign lang="la">Ludere aliquem</foreign> unclassical; <foreign lang="la">exhibere aliquem</foreign> un-Latin. To act a play, <foreign lang="la">fabulam agere</foreign> (not <foreign lang="la">fabulam docere</foreign>, which is said of the auther only). To forbid the players to act, <foreign lang="la">histrionibus ecenam interdicere</foreign> (<author>Su.</author>). The players will not act to-night, <foreign lang="la">*histriones hodie in scenam non prodibunt</foreign>.</sense></sense>
<sense pos="n" n="n." level="1">
<sense level="2"><foreign lang="la">factum</foreign> (what has been actually done): <foreign lang="la">facinus</foreign> (deed, contemplated as the act of a free agent, and as an evidence of strength of character, for good or for evil): opus (work; the product of a faciens).</sense>
<sense level="2">Acts, facta (general term): res gestae gesta, orum, sometimes res only (acts performed in the line of one’s duty or office; especially exploits, achievements in war): acta (actions performed according to particular rules; measures, e.g., of a politician): actiones (doings; goings on; implying a continued course. Herzog, ad B. Civ., 1, 5). Acts of the Apostles, *Apostolorum acta or res gestae.</sense>
<sense level="2">A noble act, egregie or egregium factum; facinus praeclarum. An immortal act, facinus or opus immortale. Honorable, glorious act, laudes, decora, plur. To perform an act, facinus facere, conticere; opus edere. A wicked act, facinus, flagitium scelus committere; scelus facere, perficere, admittere.</sense>
<sense level="2">In the very act, in manifesto facinore (e.g., to be caught, deprehendi; in re praesenti is, on the spot where the occurrence took place.</sense>
<sense level="2">Act of amnesty, oblivio sempiterna (Cic.): oblivio quam Athenienses ἀμνηστίαν vocant (Val. Max.): lex ne quis ante actarum rerum accusetur, neve multetur (a law). Vid: AMNESTY.</sense>
<sense level="2">Acts of a court, tabulae (general term): litterae publicae (archives) acta publica, or acta only (recorded proceedings of the Senate, people, or individual magistrates). To record in the acts, m acta referre. To be contained in the acts. in actis esse.</sense></sense>
</div1>